Guide to the Manchester Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Manchester papers
1697-1737
OSB MSS fc.37
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.5
(1 box) + 17 volumes
The papers contain correspondence, copies of treaties, speeches and credentials, orders, memoranda, reports, newsletters and other papers mostly relating to diplomatic, political and military affairs in western Europe during the War of the Spanish Succession. In addition to documenting Manchester's missions to the republic of Venice and the court of France, the papers provide much detail on shifting relations among the northern powers, the break between France and England following the former's recognition of James III, English concern over Jacobite activities on the Continent, and negotiations with the Low Countries and Savoy. Major correspondents writing from England on politics and diplomacy include the Earls of Albemarle, Jersey, Shrewsbury and Sunderland, and secretaries James Vernon, Robert Yard, Joseph Addison and Matthew Prior. Other correspondents include the Duke of Marlborough and J. Chetwynd, writing on military matters, and Sir P. Medows, William Blathwayt, James Cresset, Francis Schonenberg, Abraham Stanyan and Alexander Stanhope, addressing affairs in various countries. Manchester's letters to Blathwayt, located in Series II, describe life at the French court and events leading up to the French violation of the Treaty of Ryswick.
Montagu, Charles, Duke of Manchester, 1660?-1722
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Manchester Papers were purchased in 1987 from Sotheby's on Osborn funds.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Manchester Papers are a group of over 1,000 letters and other documents concerning the professional and political activities of Charles Montagu, 1st Duke of Manchester. The collection spans the dates 1697-1737, but the bulk of the material dates from between 1698 and 1708, the years of Manchester's embassies to Venice and Paris.
The collection consists of fifteen albums, two letterbooks, and one box of unbound letters. The items in the albums are arranged in a rough chronological order.
Volume 16 contains copies of letters written by Manchester to William Blathwayt and James Vernon during his service as Ambassador to Paris in 1700-01. The letters provide much information on political events, including the proclamation of the duc d'Anjou as King of Spain, the mounting preparations for war, and the break in relations between England and France following Louis XIV's recognition of James III in violation of the Treaty of Ryswick. There are descriptions of "Jacobite intrigues," life at Versailles, and events in the Low Countries.
Volume 17 contains copies of thirty letters written by Manchester in French between January and April of 1702. They are mainly brief business letters or requests for information. The letters in Box 18 consist mainly of business letters by Manchester to William Blathwayt written between 1699 and 1701.
Treaty of Ryswick (1697); Treaty of Utrecht (1713); Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697 -- Diplomatic history; Northern War, 1700-1721 -- Diplomatic history; Spanish Succession, War of, 1701-1714 -- Campaigns; Spanish Succession, War of, 1701-1714 -- Causes; Spanish Succession, War of, 1701-1714 -- Diplomatic history; France -- Court and courtiers; France -- Foreign relations -- 1643-1715; France -- History -- Louis XIV, 1643-1715; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- 1660-1714; Great Britain -- History -- 1660-1714; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1689-1702; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1702-1714; Holy Roman Empire -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Netherlands -- Foreign relations -- France -- 1648-1714; Netherlands -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain -- 1648-1714; Savoy (France and Italy) -- Foreign relations; Spain -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Venice (Italy) -- Commerce -- Great Britain; Venice (Italy) -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Venice (Italy) -- Politics and government -- 1508-1797; Diplomats -- Great Britain; Cosimo, Grand-Duke of Tuscany, III, 1642-1723; Eugene, of Savoy, Prince of Savoy, 1663-1736; James, Prince of Wales, 1688-1766; Addison, Joseph, 1672-1719; Albemarle, Arnold Joost van Keppel, Earl of, 1669-1718; Blackwell, Lambert, Sir, -1727; Blathwayt, William, 1649?-1717; Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612; Chetwynd, J.; Cressett, James, 1655?-1710; Franceschini, Paolo; Godolphin, Sidney Godolphin, Earl of, 1645-1712; Jersey, Edward Villiers, Earl of, 1656-1711; Marlborough, John Churchill, Duke of, 1650-1722; Marlborough, Sarah Jennings Churchill, Duchess of, 1660-1744; Meadows, Philip, Sir, 1626-1718; Montagu, Charles, Duke of Manchester, 1660?-1722; Montagu, James, 1568?-1618; Norris, John, Sir, 1670 or 1671-1749; Oxford, Robert Harley, Earl of, 1661-1724; Plantamour, M.; Portland, William Bentinck, Earl of, 1649-1709; Prior, Matthew, 1664-1721; Schonenberg, Francis; Shovell, Clowdisley, Sir, 1650-1707; Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718; Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716; Stanhope, Alexander, 1639-1707; Stanyan, Abraham, 1669?-1732; Sunderland, Charles Spencer, Earl of, 1674-1722; Vanbrugh, John, 1664-1726; Vernon, James, 1646-1727; Yard, Robert; England and Wales. Sovereign (1694-1702: William III); Great Britain. Sovereign (1707-1714: Anne); Great Britain. Sovereign (1714-1727: George I); Spain. Sovereign (1665-1700: Charles II); France. Sovereign (1643-1715: Louis III)
- Albums, 1697/98 Feb 8; Series I
  - R. Yard to the E of M, giving an account of business in the two Houses of Parliament. Five English regiments had arrived in Ireland from Flanders. Those previously there were "to be broke" Whitehall, 1697/98 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Instructions given by King William III to Charles, E of M, upon his appointment as Ambassador Extraordinary to the Republic of Venice. (Printed in Cole's Historical and Political Memoirs, p. 1) Kensington, 1697 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Henry James, of Queen's College, Cambridge, to the E of M, announcing that the senior Esquire Bedell had been sent to the Earl with a Patent for the office of High Steward of the University. Queen's College, 1697 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Duke of Shrewsbury to the E of M, giving him notice that he would shortly be despatched on his Embassy, and that there would be no difficulty at the Treasury with respect to money.The Duke had suggested to the King the propriety of allowing a secretary. Whitehall, 1697 Jul 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Duke of Shrewsbury to the Earl of Manchester, allowing that he would be allowed to have a Secretary of the Embassy, viz. Mr. Stanyan. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 2) Whitehall, 1697 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Earl of Portland to the E of M, regretting that the King would not make any promise with respect to the post of Exempt of the Guards, vacant through the death of Mr. Davenant. (In French.) Loo, n.y. Aug 9/19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Earl of Albemarle to the E of M, announcing that the King would allow a Secretary of the Embassy to Venice, and had given the Duke of Shrewsbury instructions to that effect. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's memoirs, p. 3) Loo, 1697 Sep 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Duke of Shrewsbury to the E of M, wishing the latter success in his capacity of public minister and "bonnes fortunes" as a young man. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 3) Grafton, 1697 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Additional instructions to the E of M, as Ambassador Extraordinary to the Republic of Venice. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 3) Whitehall, 1697 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Further additional instructions. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 4) Whitehall, 1697 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, promising to send news in a subsequent letter. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 5) Whitehall, 1697 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, giving various small items of news and gossip. Whitehall, 1697 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, thanking the latter for exerting his influence with the King to obtain an appointment for Mr. Meeres, etc. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 5) Cologne, 1697 Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Earl of Portland to the E of M, regretting that they had not met at the Hague. (In French. A translation printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 5) Whitehall, 1697 Nov 12/22 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, regretting that the Duke of Shrewsbury was compelled to leave town on account of his health, and touching the subject of military organization, etc. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 5. Whitehall, 1697 Nov 26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, to the effect that neither the Prince of Baden nor the townspeople of Nuremberg were satisfied with the terms of the Peace. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 6) Augsberg, 1697 Nov 30/20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The E of M to Sir Joseph Williamson, announcing arrival at Venice. (Draft) Venice, n.y. Dec 10/20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The E of M to the Lord Chamberlain (the Earl of Sunderland), announcing his arrival at Venice. (Draft) Venice, 1697 Dec 20/10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, announcing arrival at Venice, etc. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 7) Venice, 1697 Dec 20/1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, stating that the Earl had taken a house, and was about to make his arrival known, in form, to the Republic. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 7) Venice, 1697 Dec 27/17 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The Earl of Albemarle to the E of M, expressing a hope that the journey to Venice had been agreeable to the end. (In French) Kensington, 1697 Dec 31/21 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Statement of legal questions arising out of the wills of William Godolphin, formerly Ambassador to the Court of Spain, with prayer that the E of M might be authorized to employ his offices at Venice for a solemn hearing of a cause relating to Godolphin's money in the Bank of Venice., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, announcing that the Earl had officially notified his arrival at Venice to the Republic. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 7) Venice, 1898 Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, relating to the expected mode of official reception of the Earl as Ambassador at Venice. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 8) Venice, 1698 Jan 10 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, giving an account of proceedings in Parliament, Lord Sunderland's resignation of his staff (as Lord Chamberlain), the arrival of the Czar of Muscovy, etc. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 9) Whitehall, 1697/98 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Duke of Shrewsbury to the E of M, regretting that he had not answered the Earl's letters. Eyford, 1697/98 Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, stating that he had nothing of great importance to communicate. (Draft) Venice, 1697 Jan 7/17 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - The E of M to the Earl of Albemarle, expressing good will, and stating that his official reception at Venice had been delayed. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 8) Venice, 1697 Jan 7/17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Edward Griffith to the E of M, stating that he wrote by desire of the Prince and Princess (of Denmark) to make excuse for their delay in writing. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p.10) London, 1697/98 Jan 20/30 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, complaining of his reception having been needlessly delayed, stating that the day for it had at length been fixed, and giving some details of the political situation. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 9) Venice, 1697/98 Jan 24/14 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - R. Yard to the E of M, chiefly upon the subject of the well- known accusation against Mr. Duncombe with respect to Exchequer bills. (This letter is printed in part in Cole's Memoirs, but the most important passage, that relating to Mr. Duncombe, is omitted.) Whitehall, 1697/98 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, stating that the official reception at Venice had again been postponed, etc. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p.10) Venice, 1697/98 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, announcing the King's opinion that the Earl's stay at Venice need not continue long after the ceremony of reception, and that he doubted the expediency of establishing a Resident there. (Printed. Cole's memoirs, p. 11) Whitehall, 1697/98 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, giving a brief account of the reception and audience at Venice. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 11) Venice, 1698 Feb 7 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - The Duke of Shrewsbury to the E of M, announcing that the King was not yet disposed to sanction a visit of the Earl to the court of Turin. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 16) Eyford, 1697/98 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, stating that he hoped soon to receive the answer of the College, and bring his mission to an end. Lord Pagett had been invited by the Grand Vizier to Adrianople. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p.16) Venice, n.y. Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - R. Yard to the E of M, giving particulars of Parliamentary business, and chiefly of Mr. Duncombe's defence in the House of Commons with respect to the affair of the Exchequer bills. Whitehall, 1697/98 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Copy of a letter from Senators, etc, of thirteen Swiss Cantons to the King of France, expressing gratitude for the regard shown to their interests by him in including them in the terms of the Peace. (In Latin.) Zurich, 1698 Feb. 16 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - James Vernon to the Earl of Manchester, announcing that the account of the Earl's audience had been laid before the King, who left it to the Earl to return when he thought proper. (Printed. Cole's Memoir's, p. 16) Whitehall, 1697/98 Feb 18 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, reporting the progress of his mission, and suggesting the expediency of appointing a Resident at Venice. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 17) Venice, 1697/98 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - R. Yard to the E of M, giving an account of an unsuccessful attack, in the House of Commons, upon the Lords of the Treasury, on the subject of Exchequer bills, etc. Whitehall, 1697/98 Feb 22 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, to the effect that he had presented letters from the Prince and Princess of Denmark to the Republic, and that he hoped his mission would be followed by results beneficial to trade. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 21) Venice, 1698 Feb 28/18 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Lord Somers to the E of M, congratulating the latter upon the honours received in his Embassy, and complaining of bitter attacks on their party in the House of Commons. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 22) London, 1697/98 Mar 1 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - R. Yard to the E of M, giving an account of progress of "Mr. Duncombe's Bill" (of Pains and Penalties). Lord Durseley had been appointed Ambassador to Turkey upon the death of Sir James Rushout. Whitehall, 1697/98 Mar 1 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, expressing his intention of leaving Venice in about ten days. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 23) Venice, 1697/98 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - The E of M to Mr. Secretary Vernon, to the same effect. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 23) Venice, 1697/98 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, expressing hopes of a satisfactory reply from the Republic before his departure, and mentioning various reports in reference to foreign politics. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 24) Venice, 1698 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - R. Yard to the E of M, giving an account of the rejection of "Mr. Duncombe's Bill" by the Lords, and mentioning the arrival of Lord Paget with news from Turkey. The Duke of Shrewsbury suffered from spitting of blood. Whitehall, 1697/98 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, expressing fears that he would not have received as definite an answer as he might be desired from the Republic before leaving Venice. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 24) Venice, 1698 Mar 21 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - The Earl of Portland to the E of M, expressing a hope that the latter had enjoyed himself, especially during the carnival. (In French) Paris, n.y. Mar 21 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, announcing that he had had his audience of leave, was detained in Venice by his brother's illness, and still hoped his mission might in the end have a good effect. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 24) Venice, 1698 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, regretting further delay in leaving Venice from the same cause. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 27) Venice, 1698 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - R. Yard to the E of M, giving briefly the news of the court and an account of racing at Newmarket. There had been an indirect attempt in the House of Commons to make a precedent for admitting Mr. Duncombe to bail. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii. 41) Newmarket, 1698 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - The E of M to Mr. Yard, announcing his arrival in Paris, and requesting that the King might be asked to place a yacht at his disposal to cross the channel. He contrasts the wealth of the English visitors with the poverty of the French, everywhere to be observed. (Draft.) Paris, 1698 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, asking to have a yacht placed at his disposal, and expressing hopes that the Duke approved of his conduct as Ambassador. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 27) Paris, 1698 May 3/13 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, apologising for not having himself notified to the Duke his departure from Venice, on account of his brother's death, and mentioning prevalent rumors of a new war being imminent. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 27) Lyon, 1698 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Shrewsbury, announcing his arrival in London and the King's satisfaction with his proceedings, and recommending Mr. Stanyan as a proper person to be resident Ambassador at Venice. (Draft. Printed, in part only, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 27) London, 1698 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - The Duke of Shrewsbury to the E of M, congratulating the Earl upon his return. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 28) Grafton, 1698 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - The Duke of Shrewsbury to the E of M, informing the Earl that the King was not disposed to appoint a Resident at Venice. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 28) Grafton, 1698 Jun 4 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Speech of the E of M to the Dogeressa of Venice, containing many compliments to herself and the Doge, upon taking leave. (In Italian) (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Copy of the credentials given by William III to the E of M for presentation to the Doge of Venice, upon the appointment of the Earl as Ambassador Extraordinary. (In Latin) Kensington, 1697 Apr 21 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Copy of a letter from King William III to a person unnamed (but who, from internal evidence, must have been Lord Somers, the Lord Chancellor), requesting him to send secretly "the full powers under the Great Seal with the names in blank to treat with C Tall." (i.e. Count Tallard), concerning the succession of the Kingdom of Spain. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 30, and Tindal's continuation of Rapin, vol. ii, p. 456) Loo, 1698 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Copy of the answer, without signature, in which the writer (Lord Somers) says that he has "put the Seal to the Commission without expecting the return of the warrant," that "the Commission is wrote by Mr. Secretary, and no other creature has the least knowledge of anything besides the persons already named," viz. "Mr. Mount. (Charles Montagu, Chancellor of the Exchequer), Lord Orford, and the Duke of Shrewsbury." In this answer the advantages and disadvantages of the proposed treaty for the partition of Spain are discussed. (Printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 30, and, with a slight variation, in Tindal's continuation of Rapin, vol. ii p. 458) Turnbridge Wells, 1698 Aug 28 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - The E of M's first speech to the Venetian Senate, expressing hopes of the continuance of friendship between England and Venice. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 11) (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - The E of M's speech upon delivering letters from the Prince and Princess of Denmark to the Venetian Senate. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p.22) (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Answer of the Senate to the above speech. (Italian, with translation at foot. Very brief. The translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 23), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Answer of the Senate to the first speech of the E of M, expressing cordial sentiments towards the King of England and his Ambassador. (In Italian, with translation. The translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 12) (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Speech of the E of M upon the occasion of presenting his "First Memorial" at Venice, in which he calls attention to the chief points, viz: Redress for injuries to British subjects, especially seamen; removal of restraints on trade as affecting British subjects; the case of the ships "Mary" and "Samuel and Mary"; and justice to the right heirs of Sir Wm. Godolphin. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 17) (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Copy of the First Memorial (to which reference is made above) in full. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 18), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Answer of the Senate to the speech made by the E of M (on presenting his first Memorial), expressing a desire to act in accordance with the wishes of the English Government. (Italian, with translation. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 21), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Speech of the E of M, made at his audience of leave at Venice, in which he expresses disappointment at not having received a satisfactory answer to his Memorial before his departure. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 25), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Answer of the Senate to the Memorial of the E of M, and to his speech at the audience of leave, in which particulars are given of the mode of dealing (past and future) with British merchants, with British subjects in Venetian courts, and British seamen entering the Venetian navy, and promises are given that, after due enquiry, justice shall be done with respect to the specific subjects of complaint. (In Italian) (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Translation of the above answer. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 25), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, giving a few particulars respecting the attitude of the Danes, the Duke of Holstein, and the French ministers in the North. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 91) Hamburg, 1699 Jan 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Signor Girolamo Duodo to the E of M, expressing hopes of the settlement of the claims of the heirs of the late Sir William Godolphin. (In Italian) Venice, 1699 Jan 23 (Box 2, Folder 2)